Guide to the Dept. of Sociology Records, 1953-1990.
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Dept. of Sociology records 1953-1990
University Archives, Duke University
Duke University. Dept. of Sociology.
0.5 Linear Feet 750 Items
The Dept. of Sociology at Duke was established in 1930 by Charles Abram Ellwood (1873-1946) and remains an active department to this day offering degrees to both undergraduates and graduate students.
This collection contains student research papers, course syllabi, memoranda, newspaper clippings, documentation from the Sociology Majors Union, as well as other various departmental documents.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Provenance
The Dept. of Sociology Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in May 22, 1995.
Historical Note
The Dept. of Sociology at Duke was established in 1930 by Charles Abram Ellwood (1873-1946) and remains an active department to this day offering degrees to both undergraduates and graduate students. This department seeks to educate students on the scientific study of society, including patterns of social relationships, social interaction, and culture. At Duke the department was known as the Dept. of Sociology and Anthropology until 1972 when the two fields split into separate departments.
Collection Overview
This collection contains student research papers, course syllabi, memoranda, newspaper clippings, documentation from the Sociology Majors Union, as well as other various departmental documents.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Duke University. Dept. of Sociology
Duke University -- Faculty
Duke University -- History -- 20th century.
Duke University -- Students
Related Material
Preliminary Inventory of the Dept. of Cultural Anthropology Records, 1973-1992.
University Archives, Duke University.
Preliminary Inventory of the Charles A. Ellwood papers, 1890-1946.
University Archives, Duke University.
Inventory of the Edgar Tristram Thompson papers, 1915-1985.
University Archives, Duke University.
Inventory of the Edward A. Tiryakian Papers, 1963-2008.
University Archives, Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Dept. of Sociology Records, 1953-1990, 1 Box
  - ASTRA, Inc. Proposal: The Impact of the Space Era, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Departmental, 1970; 1972
  - Memoranda, Chair J.C. McKinney: Proposal for a Center for Southern Studies in the Social Sciences and Humanities to be established at Duke, 1964
  - Papers. Winsborough, H.H. "Halbwachs' and American Studies of Urban Structure."
  - "Readings in Science and Sociology," 1953
  - Student Papers. Holmes, Daniel. "The Black Student Alliance: An Historical Look at Duke's Major Black Student Organization," 1990
  - Student Papers. Roycroft, Jane "Traditional Views of Women in Education and the Effect of Educational Desegregation on the Position of Academic Women at Duke University from Alice Mary Baldwin to Ernestine Friedl," 1980
  - Sociology Majors Union, Sociology Department, 1974-1981
  - Sociology Majors Union, minutes of general and Executive Council meetings; lists of majors, faculty, advisors; announcements and flyers, 1979-1980
  - Sociology Majors Union, "Retrenchment" and the Sociology Department, 1979-1980
  - Syllabi - Sociology 244S "Human Ecology and the Human Systems," Joel Smith, Fall 1978